software engineering radio episode 53
product line engineering part 1
welcome to software engineering radio in
this episode Michael and myself Marcus
will discuss product line engineering
and software product lines in general so
Michael I think you you will start I
guess you should listen to this episode
when you don't develop one of products
but multiple products in the same domain
so related products or similar products
so what could be some of the examples of
related or similar products so our
listeners can relate to what you mean so
for example when you build a car
infotainment system you are typically
driven by the automobile vendors as a
delivery company delivering the
infotainment system to that company and
so BMW has very distinct requirements on
the feature set and the GUI and
everything off the entertainment system
then for example Audie has and you as a
vendor for of infotainment systems you
have to deal with that basically have to
deal with those variations in
requirements and you cannot afford to
build the products that the infotainment
systems every time from scratch but you
have to reuse your artifacts and that is
exactly one of the core topics the reuse
how do you organize the reuse in your
development to reduce your development
cost yeah I think another example of
product line development could be mobile
phones if you take a look at today's
mobile phones where you get a new phone
every three weeks then those phones are
really just incremental developments
over the previous phones so if you have
a product line that helps you come up
with new software releases new
combinations of features you know the
one with camera the other one without
cameras
then having product lines will increase
your productivity so this is again
situation where product lines are are
often used a good indicator and whether
your domain actually needs a product
line or not is looking at your
development when people already started
building platforms to foster reuse it is
a good sign that you are actually
developing a product line so what are
some of the the reasons why you would
like to do product lines I think one
primary reason is probably that the
efficiency of development is going to be
higher so you're going to be cheaper and
faster and better probably in building
new variations of your system or new
products in your product line yeah as as
we already discussed there's the topic
of reuse and whenever you have the
feeling that you could do better by
reusing artifacts from one product
development to the next product
development and that is a good sign and
and so people start typically developing
platforms and the platform then contains
all the common artifacts plus very often
many generic artifacts because well you
typically want to prepare yourself for
all kinds of variations potential
variations that you might not even know
today and so the second for me one of
the key reasons to switch to software
product line development instead of just
platform development is the drama of
platform development who doesn't know
about situations when you develop the
platform two years later the complexity
of the platform just grew out of every
range you're not able to manage the
platform anymore
everybody just bashes about a platform
where light we need to build a new
platform with this new technology and
the old technology just is not
sufficient anymore so and at the end you
then have trouble hitting the market
with your products because you're so
stuck and all those platform development
and you you never really get to the
actual products to develop the products
and so these are some of the key
indicators and that you actually do
something wrong or maybe your your
paradigm that you're developing in is
not sufficient so what then is the key
difference between developing a platform
which you want to reuse and product line
development well software product line
engineering provides you with a frame
for the development of your platform you
still have a platform and actually
looking at some of the definitions of
software product line engineering it is
defined as developing on with on the
basis of platforms so it's platform
development and mass customization and
here the mass customization brings in
all those variability that this
flexibility that you need that this
derivation of individual products from
that platform so mass customization
means that instead of actually
creatively building a product which is a
member of the family or of the product
line you rather take some configuration
language a configuration tools some
means of specifying the features you
need for your product then you press a
couple of buttons and the configured
customized product falls out of the end
of the product line or yeah that is kind
of the idealistic view but in general
every method every tool every concept is
fine as long as it helps to increase the
level of abstraction that is the key
thing and so here model driven
development or generic approaches help
but another key thing is that you
explicitly deal with with variability
and you you do that at all phases at all
times and you remove variability and
that is one of the key effectors I see
why platforms become outdated and and
just die because nobody really looks
the variability they support and nobody
dares to remove any variability that is
no longer needed okay so before we
explain some of the more detailed topics
like variability management and then
some multiple aspects I think I'd like
to point out that product line
development increases the efficiency and
and room reduces cost in a in a long
term view so it's not something that
will help you you know if you have the
the problem today it's probably not
going to help you today it's something
yeah it's a strategic thing that you
have to do when you do product line
engineering yes it's something totally
inconvenient I would say it's something
that you must have felt enough pain to
switch to unless you fell the pain and
you you maybe lost your market shares
and you had real trouble with your
development you most probably not going
to switch to a software product line
engineering approach because it just
requires too much effort too much
upfront investment too much discipline
of all stuff I mean when we later
discuss feature modeling when we later
discuss configuration management product
error evasion it's all really
complicated and tedious stuff but it
helps you at the end to reduce the cost
of development okay so some of the
drivers are if you have to have
developed products for different
platforms if you have rapid changes on
the marketplace you have to redo very
you know you have to deliver products in
short iterations and maybe if you have
related similar but not identical
products in a certain domain these are
the key drivers why you would want to go
to a product language in engineering
yeah but also the domain itself should
stay stable if the domain is changing
that you're developing the products for
it's hard to to keep track and and the
upfront investment might be lost again
yeah so you say if you develop
automotive and infotainment systems
today mobile phones tomorrow and
insurance enterprise systems in a week
then this is probably in you know it
doesn't
pay off to invest in a certain product
line if you if your domain changes all
over yeah if the domain changes that
dramatically but even smaller changes in
the domain like shifting what form a
focus were from for example navigation
systems to then pure entertainment
systems to pure mp3 players or so this
might be already enough of a change to
endanger your platform your product line
investments so that's probably the
reason why maybe the first step in
product line engineering is what some
people call domain scoping which tries
to suggest that you have to define where
your domain begins and where it ends and
probably the narrower the more narrow
you define your domain that the easier
it is to come up with a good workable
and and pragmatic platform
yes coping is very important to limit
the investment to to really get focused
and and well of course focusing is
already is always good but it really has
an impact on on the business case the
business case is something maybe when I
talk to the sei people software
engineering Institute people who are
leading the research community and in
software product line engineering when I
talk to them they say the business case
is the most important thing so I'm as an
engineer
I am I as an engineer don't like to
think about business cases but somebody
in your organization should really think
about a business case whether it's
actually worthwhile to invest in a
platform to invest in a product line or
just do one off development for every
customer request so keep that in mind
the business case is important but now
we talk about the other stuff
ok so I think we should start or
continue actually by explaining a couple
of key concepts one is project
development versus one of system
development versus product line
development yeah in our company where I
work for we typically have system
development or we have product
development product development means
that the the feature said you deliver to
individual customers is always or almost
the same that you don't have really
shrink-wrap software in our company but
we have products that are as they are
there was a little customization but the
customization is mostly configuration
and so it's not a big deal and it's not
a key development effort to customize
the solution to to a specific customer
still it's very hard because every
customer has of course wishes that he
tries to bring into your product and the
different roles in your organization for
example sales and development always
struggle and fight on which internals to
change for this specific customer and
which things to keep to keep the
development smooth and easy system
development on the other side that is or
system or solution development here you
fully adopt the changes that the
individual customer requests and you
basically do a one-off development for
this single customer you do a solution
instead of a product and this has the
the problems that of course the customer
requires you to maintain the solution
and he will also wants to benefit of all
the new features and you basically have
to develop all the new features for all
branches in your configuration
management where you typically keep the
solutions for all individual solutions
that you ever build you have to deliver
potentially this new feature and so you
have a huge effort to bring in those new
features and well a typical approach is
to use platforms for this but that's
just not sufficient to deal with all the
changes to deal with the variability you
have you need to have a strong
variability management so to say so what
do you say is that product line
engineering and the techniques we're
going
to talk about indecent in subsequent
episodes are important for product as
well as for system development right
both both disciplines but both kind of
businesses heavily benefit from adopting
a software product line approach okay
and and maybe to to care about some of
the more enterprise related terminology
where people talk about projects where
you go to a customer or where some
customer comes to you as a consulting
firm and says hey develop me the system
of whatever j2ee this is basically
system development it's also a one-off
system of course if your company builds
I don't know insurance systems all over
again then you might want to adopt a
product line approach internally to be
able to deliver to your customer
insurance applications faster customer
need not necessarily know that not
necessarily know that you're actually
using product line techniques yeah two
other terms that we know used already in
our conversation where product line and
product family and the term product line
well can can also be used and is often
be used to to identify products that are
in the same portfolio of a vendor but
not necessarily have any assets in
common they are not constructed or made
of of the same artifacts whereas the
term product family means today the same
in the in the product line engineering
company community but has stronger hand
on the commonality or under on the
common ancestors from of the common core
assets so that the build the product was
built from I've read a definition of
software system family or product family
which says basically that a set of
products is a product family if it's
worthwhile to look at the commonalities
between the products before you look at
the specific differences isn't that by
partners or so might be and I don't know
somewhere in my slides I don't know
where I had copied it from okay too
to illustrate the other thing the the
non-technical product line if you go to
IBM you'll see that they have a whole
range of WebSphere products they have
the WebSphere application developer they
have WebSphere application server they
have WebSphere everyplace I think and
they have WebSphere MQ the first one is
an eclipse-based development environment
the second is j2ee application server
number three is an OSGi implementation
and number four is MQ series rebranded
and obviously since these are completely
different systems for completely
different technical domains they
certainly have no no common code and not
an IBM er so I don't know but I would
also based on their history I don't
think there is any common code however
they're all part of the WebSphere
product line and that's clearly a
marketing term or a it wants to suggest
some some you know things that work
together or whatever so that's not what
we talk about we talk about products
that have technical similarities they're
built in a common platform and where as
we will see variabilities between the
products are managed explicitly yeah in
this episode we talk about software
product lines but there is also the term
product line in general and so not only
focusing on software but on Hardware
electrics electronics and software and
so this is actually a true research
topic combining all the different
disciplines of hardware and software and
it's it's truly challenging to build
systems with a product line where both
disciplines hardware and software are
involved but for this episode and and
this we focus on and software product
lines although as you said most product
lines are in the context of embedded
systems and most of them have some
hardware aspect to it and just to
mention that that's one of the reasons
why the OMG started the seuss ml
modeling language which is basically a
UML dialect that can be used also for
systems modeling so it did include
hardware but that's a different topic
you might have to talk to Tim Wilkins I
guess
to other for me very important terms to
get the rest of the terminology straight
as the understanding of a problem and a
solution space this goes back to the
book by Gustav charnetski generic
programming where he true generative
programming generative programming where
he drew some diagrams where he separated
out the problem and solution space and
so I like this analogy very much and
like to use it for explaining product
lines and and so the problem space here
you talk about the requirements to use
cases ideally even scenarios and and
non-functional requirements and at the
highest level of abstraction and for
what's really important for product
lines you talk about domain modeling
here I would just refer to the interview
with Eric Evans in our podcast and in
the solution space you talk about well
at this lowest level of abstraction all
the API calls all the source code but
also about the architecture the frame
words that you potentially use and in a
in a software product line most probably
also configurable components you talk
then about your DSL the domain-specific
language which you might use to
configure your your system to
instantiate it and of course I have to
to comment on this one since this is
very much model driven development stuff
so the idea of the solution and the
problem space is obviously very related
to what we talked about more in modular
and development where we have the models
that represent the problem space then
you have some transformation which
transforms the variability or whatever
else you described in your model into
implementation structures which is the
solution space and I think one thing is
really important to understand in the
context of product line engineering
people often talk about configuration
so one reason for using domain-specific
languages in product line engineering is
to describe the configuration of the
product using terms defined in the
problem space and then you have
transformations that kind of find out
how the how your solution space
structure has to look like in order to
realize the configuration described by
at the DSL so in this context dsls are
configuration languages
however if you look at the more I don't
know traditional look at model driven
development if you design for example
the component structure of a system then
you probably wouldn't call this
configuration because you creatively
compose a system from atomic building
blocks in this case components so the
important thing here is that there is a
continuum for modeling languages or
domain-specific languages in the
simplest case your language is just I
don't know a five tuple of boolean's
right so you can specify I need this
feature I need this feature feature I
don't need that one don't need that one
and I don't need that one so the whole
configuration is just basically tagging
five check boxes or checking five check
boxes on the other extreme the
configuration language can actually be
used to configure complex frameworks and
you can actually draw diagrams and you
draw graphs or used the complex textural
modeling notations to really describe
complex
yeah configuration data structures and
in that case people don't call it
configuration anymore people typically
call this programming with the DSL and
so this this this this continuum between
configuration on the one hand side and
as often as he called it once creative
construction on the other side this is
these are really two extremes of
continuum and and your language can be
used for for all in the mediate steps
and we'll talk about some of these
details in later episodes but I think
it's important to mention yeah you
mentioned already an important other
term that is feature and future modeling
and feature models represent
the variability and the commonality in
your problem space using features and
for individual features you typically
have a keyword or combination of
keywords by which you identify a certain
feature and you organize that
hierarchically so you to keep them
overview and typically the such a
feature model is used in for deriving
later the checkboxes on which you
specify your configuration because on
every variation point you have to make
selections whether to choose a feature
or not or select alternatives etc so
there is relationships between the
features things like if you have that
feature you cannot have this feature
also or if you have this feature you
have to choose one of the following
three other features in order to make
this definition complete yeah besides
the hierarchy besides a hierarchical
structure
you also have relations among the
features with constrains and
recommendations if you select this
feature you have or you should use also
this other feature because this makes
sense or is required to make this a bit
more understandable I'd like to just
briefly mention an example consider the
concept aeroplane it has a feature wing
there is no aeroplane without a wing
right so this is a recommended feature
that every every member of the product
line aeroplane has to have however you
can have a wing that is low one that is
high and then what is one is that's on
your shoulder so you have three
different arrangements of wings so if
you build an airplane you have to have
the feature wing and then you have to
set select one of the following three
sub features which would be a high wing
shoulder wing or low wing and there are
other things for example there is an
optional feature for airplanes which is
the engine if you if your airplane
doesn't have an engine it's still an
airplane it's a sail plane right so but
if you select the feature engine then
you have to also select what
kind of engine you have which is
typically either a piston engine or a
jet engine turbine so you have to select
one of these two so a feature model
basically describes a kind of grammar a
set of constraints that you have to
follow when you select the specific
combinations of features for your
specific product so you can then
basically take a suitable tool we might
want to talk about some in the future in
future episodes where you just click you
know I I want to have an engine and then
the tool says okay but then you also
have to decide which kind of engine so a
feature model helps you come up with a
correct configuration of features that
will result in a workable and useful
product then next I would like to
discuss the term platform we use it
already and but in the context of
software product lines it's important to
have a clear view on what a platform is
all about and in this context a platform
is not the set of libraries that you use
to derive your products from it is much
more well it might be the libraries it
might be the software as it might be all
the software components that you have of
course but then it's also the test
scripts the the requirements the feature
models the domain model especially its
base else generators young works it's
all the core assets which is just
another term very often used in the
community it's it's all the core assets
that you use to derive your concrete
products applications from and there are
two to kind of views on the platform one
is with a minimalist approach saying you
put everything in the platform that is
common to all products or a maximalist
approach you put everything in the
platform that is common and you put
everything in that is variable that is
that is somehow used to derive one of
the products it's and it's still
contained in the platform but but then
how is the product configuration process
different if you have a minimalist
approach that means you have to add
application specific stuff as
opposed to having a maximalist
approached and you would just remove
stuff you don't need or you might
configure it out at runtime or whatever
yes exactly
so which one is preferable or is it is
it a question of non-functional
requirements like in the embedded space
where you don't have you know enough
space to carry around all the baggage of
a maximalist platform you might have a
minimalist and add stuff well I guess
well I I've seen projects succeed with
with either approach but personally I
prefer to have a minimalist approach so
that is my platform and the rest are
just assets that I carry around I don't
call it that phone because it's often
confused with the maximalist approach
but I I keep those things around in
configuration management to later derive
my products from right yeah that's the
way I do it too since I'm more in this
model driven world I always have a
platform of reusable generic frameworks
and components and then they are used
the DSL to configure them or to add
specific application specific stuff on
top of it
but here we are at a point where it's
it's crucial how you do the
configuration management how you do the
product derivation whether you keep
derived products in your configuration
management or whether you only keep the
core assets in the in the configuration
management do the derivation and just
describe the rules how you derive the
concrete product from it so the concrete
product is not instantiated and then
stored in configuration management it's
just the rules that are stored but that
is a whole big other topic but but that
hints to something we discussed briefly
in when we prepared this episode and
that is that product line engineering is
especially interesting if you have to
keep a number of those different
products valid over a long time if you
you know if you for example if you're
building engine controllers four four
six and eight cylinder engines with one
two four and six liters of whoo-whoo
combustion volume I don't know
cubic centimeters you car freaks know
what I'm talking about I don't know so
if you have to be able to keep all those
current
and reproducible at the same time then
product line engineering that's another
reason for doing it if you just you know
develop version wonderful product today
and tomorrow you're developed version
two and don't care about version one
anymore
then that might not be such a you know
powerful reason to make you go product
line
yeah the the next thing is variability
and we we talked about it already about
it variability is a key element in
software product line engineering and
you have variability in the feature
model but you also have variability then
of course in the implementation and you
need to link basically the solutions
base variability the variation points
that is the points the locations in the
source code the locations in your
generator in your model ocean space the
solution space with the problem space
where you do the selections or where you
draw your DSL model and so the the means
to implement variability in the solution
space is in my opinion pretty well known
besides the the the trend and model twin
software development where there's still
research in in some areas but the
classical approach having a strategy for
example for implementing some runtime
variability or having macros and in c
c++ or having templates in c++ to to
have a certain variability and then this
is pretty well known important in the
context of the solution space
variability in implementation
variability is the binding time when do
you want to bind this variability
binding means decide about decide about
and not make it changeable anymore you
can do it at one time of course at one
time you you might be able to change it
but you can also think of binding time
at instantiation or even compile or
length time when you do certain
configurations binding of your
variability so and and the reasons of
choosing one over the other are
typically non-functional so you know if
you want to be able to change stuff at
run time during while the product is
running at your customer and it's not
good to use an early binding time for
you
abilities because you can't change them
and run them anymore however if you do
it at run time things are typically
slower and and you know how to carry
around more baggage so just as a comment
although Michael said that these
variability implementation mechanisms
are pretty well known we'll still have
an episode on them and also show some of
the not so very well known means of
handling very abilities such as aspect
orientation and metaprogramming so we'll
we'll cover this in more detail in
future episodes so what you say then in
the end is that assume you have a
platform and a set of libraries a set of
primitive building blocks that provide
the respective variabilities the
challenge of product lines is to
formally describe the mapping from
solution space variability from the
problem space variability down to the
solution space variability that's what a
stand egg and channel etske called I
think the production plan or something
like that or the production knowledge in
generative programming and of course
being a model driven guy I'd say that
one of the ways for doing that not the
only one but one of the ways is actually
using transformations as model driven
development advertisers to do some yeah
and I I just had in conversation at at
the software product lines conference
about whether a DSL is already in the
problem or in the solution space and you
can't be in either I would say it for me
is always in the solution space so the
main model the the knowledge that entity
is described they are in the in the
problem space and the generator at least
a generator and I that is for me to call
part of the DSL that is in the solutions
plan so okay my terminology maybe is
different that DSL is the language with
which you describe your models and and
whether this is part of the problem
space or the dilute solution space
depends on what you describe with your
models for example you can easily say
that you describe the configuration of
some whatever system in the problem
space space using a suitable DSL and
then you use a model to model
transformation that that generates
another model which contains things like
components Message Queuing stuff which
would be the solution space but that can
still be described with the DSL it's
just a different DSL at if a DSL that
has a different matter model and
therefore describes different things but
I put already in some some brain and
that is for me the key differentiation
of course I did put III I also put in
some some brain and thoughts and and
work into deriving a future model in the
in the in the problem space I put in
some some thoughts into developing the
domain model but as soon as I started
with transformations I feel this is
already a step towards the solution to
towards the solution space absolutely I
agree that the transformation part is
that the the way your transformations
look like they are obviously related to
the solution space otherwise you
couldn't write the transformation so if
you if you consider it typically
whatever what a code generator typically
does is first you have the model as an
input then you validate the model
against some main specific constraints
in case of feature models it's just the
semantics of the feature model below in
case of other DSL it's some other
constraints that you define as power of
the matter model once these constraint
checks validate and there are no errors
in there and and all this happens that's
all problem space there is nothing about
what you transform it to yet then the
next step is the transformation of the
generation that is obviously specific to
the solution space so even have you if
you have several solution spaces several
target platforms then you have the same
model in the DSL you have the same
constraints and then you have several
transformations one for each solution
space one for each target platform one
for each whatever you call this so and
that's why I would say that the
transformation the cogeneration aspect
is definitely part of the solution space
however the model from which you
generate and the constraints against
which you validate the model that can be
problem space depending on the
abstraction level of whatever you model
with the DSL and since the l India's L
stands for language I tend to see this
on the left side right the DSL for me
the syntax the metamodel and the
constraints whereas the back-end part is
not the DSL that's the infrastructure to
transform DSL models into something
that's executable but again that's just
my my view but I have to say it ok I
mean I it's ok with me too if you if you
see it that way and I and I can
understand this view though I my last
argument is that even a customer should
then be able to come up with this DSL
with this language and so this is my
measure everything in the problem space
a customer should be able a customer who
is not an IT specialist in software
engineering and software engineer should
come up with the problem space artifacts
yeah he should be able to come up with
the the notions the metamodel whatever
you want to describe maybe a nice syntax
by doing some sketches the customer
might not be able to come up with the
tooling to build the models my customers
who weren't able to come up with a meta
model yeah but that's some kind of
ontology that describes that the terms
that are important in the relationships
and then then you as it as a IT guy you
you take that and formalize that into a
meta model ok and the tool battle begins
see and I see already the formalization
step being moving that into the solution
space what does this have to do with a
solution space I can conceptualize a
problem space and define a meta model
that is absolutely unrelated to any
implementation stuff
okay this is the fine border where we
are okay so I think we leave it there we
have to fight this out at some okay so
let's get maybe we cut this out maybe
not anyway so um where were we we were
at explaining the the variability
especially in the solution space and I
think we were so far true through with
with the core terms may be something
related is the term or the concept of
software factories software factories is
an initiative and methodology defined by
some Microsoft guys check Greenfield and
Keith short and Stuart Kent and some
others
Steve Koch and they basically made use
of the software product line engineering
know-how and and the methodology and the
concepts and enriched it with what they
call guidance and context and they
separated out model driven development
as a separate principle or mechanic
technique to use but I actually would
have seen multiple development as part
of software product line engineering
what what's very common to use for
product management is a common
implementation technique for a product
line engineer but it can be used outside
of product lines alright so that is a
related topic and maybe we have some
interview or some somebody talk about
that later we'll see going to get
Christoph charnetski in front of the mic
okay then I think there are another
tough topics to discuss in the future
and one we already hinted at about this
is the implementation variability what
you could do there this is most
interesting for us software engineers
another your hot topic would be may all
the variability stuff how do you
describe your abilities and discuss more
about future modeling and these kinds of
things so so before we finish this one I
kind of wanted
to play devil's advocate and and and ask
what my question that is whenever I read
about talk about or discuss about
product line engineering I kind of have
the problem that I can't really touch it
you know there is no product line tool
so is it correct to say that product
line engineering is more like a mindset
and and some guidelines for process and
stuff whereas if you want to really do
it you need a lot of things that you
know that have that chip under different
flags like model development aspect
orientation feed remodeling frameworks
component based development whatever so
it's if you talk about product line
engineering is the technology the
problem or is it really more a process
framework and mindset kind of thing
well yes software product line
engineering for me is also not really
touchable there is no tool there are
tools that but they cover only parts and
there's there's a community there is
knowledge there's books there's
experience there's like success stories
yes I think at the core it's a mindset
and what I also heard is well it's just
software engineering done right I mean
whatever you would do to succeed in your
domain in successfully developing those
multiple products this is what I heard
just somebody famous from the a osde
community as say and and I was smiling
and I could just agree yes I mean
there's nothing artificial there's
nothing so special about it it's it's
just a set of best practices it's a set
of principles and what I actually strive
to do is it's a set of patterns I
believe coming back to to our to
Michael's famous topic yeah I believe
you you can derive some key principles
and product line engineering and you can
derive some key patterns that describe
the principles and and make use of them
so that it's truly applicable and well
there is also not something like
the bro decline engineering process
there are some some some techniques
there are some some important process
steps that you need to follow and there
is a certain requirement on the maturity
that we didn't talk about about and
maturity of an organization right and
also of a domain if you don't understand
you domain it's probably not very
feasible to come out with a product line
approach for it yeah so there there's no
single process for for it so it's the
same as with the HL methodologies with
the which is again another investing
topic how to combine HR methodologies
and product line engineering really
challenging again
so well today you have to read a lot of
literature you need to talk to people
who who did it and you just need to try
it and maybe make just the better
platform and and and and care about the
platform maintain it think about the
variability and things like that to do
software product line engineering today
okay and since we kind of agreed that
product line engineering is this
umbrella over some of MAS some
specialized more specific techniques
we'll cover some of these specific
techniques in subsequent episodes some
of them we have already kept our modular
development and we'll cover others in
the future anything else you want to say
thanks for listening bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details